[Music]
hey hey
welcome to connecting with code uh the
way this camp works is it is a video uh
which you're watching now
um and you try to follow along with this
video to do the same things that i'm
doing so you actually like work the
video
and you learn about coding in the
process this year what we're doing is
we're doing scratch
we have two weeks of scratch events this
first week is kind of for a k-3 focus
but really it's for anybody that hasn't
done much coding and what we're going to
be doing is we're going to be doing
games
there's a number of different games that
we've got lined up they're kind of all a
little food themed for fun
it starts with alphabet breakfast that's
what we're going to be doing today
then in day two we're gonna be building
a game called hedgehog snack
um and then day three is fish lunch fair
warning day three is the hard one right
so that's like the middle of the week
the hardest thing
um and then catching dinner is four um
and then we finish on kind of a lighter
one
called kaleidoscope dessert and somebody
different my daughter mckinley is going
to be leading that one which is going to
be fun
this material by the way it was made by
me i'm at rose-hulman so this
material is presented by rose-hulman it
was also developed by bob schaefer
so he's not on camera here with us but
he helped develop all the material
and he's at mission college which is out
in california
and so we're partnering this year to
bring you connecting with code
and the way this works is in these
videos i'm not just here by myself
i'm actually with my family and my
family is going to serve as my campers
so i'm going to go and have my family
introduce themselves me
i will start with uh with our first
camper what's your name camper
neela how old is neela five and i
go into preschool yeah so neela is five
and so who's helping neela and she's
five
mommy yeah mommy's helping uh who's our
next camper bowen and how old are you
and how old are you bowen and so bowen
seven and so mommy is helping neela a
lot
um and she's helping bowen just a little
less so
at seven and five they can do it with
mommy's help then i've got my campers
who do it all by themselves
so first camper doing it by yourself
what's your name um i am
keegan fisher and how old are you i am
nine years old and i am instilled good
so he's nine but he's been coding for a
while so he's going to be doing it by
himself and
our final camper i'm mckinley and i am
10 years old
and she is an experienced coder and
she's definitely doing it
by herself so that's the campers that i
have with me here today
so what are we going to do today so
today what we're doing is we're building
a scratch app this whole week is coding
in scratch
scratch is a website that you'll go to
uh to where you build things and learn
how to code hopefully a lot of people
have heard about scratch
let's show a demo of what we're trying
to make today so today we're making one
called alphabet breakfast
so this is the solution so you're just
kind of watching for a minute and the
solution
and the idea of this app let me go and
make a full screen here
is that you are avery so avery is
walking around collecting things
and she has to collect food in
alphabetical order wow
so the first thing she collected there
was an apple um anybody know what she
needs to collect next
what starts with b banana yeah i nearly
got it so a banana
um and if i try to eat the wrong thing
let's say i try to eat an egg next does
e egg start with c not really so it just
says keep trying food should be eaten
alphabetically so i got to find a
c food anybody
see a good c food okay cake
and so we eat cake what comes after cake
you think
donut donut uh after donut
egg
and then she does a little dance so
that's what we're building today it's a
long song i guess
that's what we're building today and
that's our goal and we're going to be
building it up
uh with a block based programming
language called scratch
and we're going to be learning a lot of
great things today these are kind of
like our learning objectives maybe i'll
come
reflect on these at the end what you
need to do is you need to go to this
website
scratch.mit.edu
you can see scratch was first made when
it was at mit
and it's grown so much since then when
you're on this scratch page your first
choice
is you can either just get started which
is great you'll just click on create if
you want
or if you like you can sign in it
doesn't matter to me if you sign in or
not
i'm in general i think that you should
because your work will will be saved
more permanently to your account
but it's pretty easy to sign up and if
you want to do that you can just pause
the video
and go do that on your own so campers
are you ready to get started
yes yes all right everybody click on
create
when you click on create it makes a new
program
um whenever you have a new program uh
you get to see the editor here
uh the editor is broken into a lot of
different places
let's just talk about it some so we're
more familiar with scratch
this area right over here this upper
right is called the stage
below the stage are the different actors
that are like on the stage
um sprites ah shoot i gave it away
scratch calls them the special name does
anybody know what the special name is
sprite i gave away the answer so they're
called sprites we have one sprite right
now
but we can actually have many sprites
sprites have code so each sprite has
their own code
the code is over here in the left in the
toolbar let's drag over
one line of code so drag over move 10
so now you can see that our cat has code
that he can run
move10 so the question is how do we run
this code
well one way to run it is to double
click on it so double click on where it
says move 10
and you'll notice something about your
mouse every time you double click it
he'll go over to the right now one fun
thing is you can also just kind of drag
them back over here
and you can double click it and you can
run it some more
eventually you'll get bored with doing
this so once you're bored with this
let's let's do some more things now
double clicking on it is one way to run
code
but a much better way to run code is to
add
a when green flag clicked so let's
look at these uh commands if you scroll
down through here there's some blue ones
uh and then there's some purple ones and
then there's some yellow ones and maybe
you call that orange
and there's a lot of commands to make it
easier to get around the commands
they're broken into categories
um the category we want is events so
click on
over here on the far left where it says
events and it'll scroll you to that
section of the code so you can kind of
see that these things they just help you
scroll around
to find the right category so the most
common way to run
code is to grab this when green flag
clicked and put it and just snap it
right on top of your code
so this is what most scratch programs
look like so this is considered like the
start of the program
so our cat when the green flag is
clicked
he's going to move 10. let's try it a
couple times so click on
the green flag and he'll move he'll move
across the stage
so this is just to kind of get you
familiar with the environment
that we're working in but actually we we
don't need a cat at all in this game if
you remember looking at the solution
there are no cats in there so we don't
need this particular sprite
so what i want to do is i want to delete
this sprite so he was just a test
to delete it some of my campers found
this already
there's a trash can i got over here and
if you click this trash can icon
the cat will be gone poof if you ever do
something like that on accident
campers how do you how do you fix a
problem if you did that on accident
yeah command z or control z depending on
what type of computer you're on uh
that's undo so if i messed up
i just hit um uh control z or command z
uh oops that didn't work you can also go
to edit uh restore sprite and it'll just
be back right
i did want to delete them that was a
good thing to do but just know that undo
is very important with things you're
doing
all right now let's add a new sprite
i've got a sprite that i'm planning on
you're using
her name is avery walking so what we
want to do
is we want to add a new sprite to do
that
there's a circle down here for choose a
sprite
this circle confuses me a little bit
because what happens is when i hover
over it it like shoots up this thing
it turns out you can ignore the thing
that pops up you can just click right on
the circle
so click right on the circle and what
we're going to do is we're going to add
a different sprites
instead of that cat and i'm looking for
one called avery walking
now i can see avery walking is right
here so i'm just going to select it
but just know that when you're looking
for sprites you can search for them in
here
you can also organize them by category
lots of options
but i want avery walking so when i click
on her
she's now into my scratch project
avery um is uh looking pretty good
she's a little big so what i want to do
is i want to make her
a little smaller so right here is the
size
the size right now is set to 100 that
means 100 percent
of her normal size make her some amount
smaller
i'm going to go with 60. so now she'll
be able to
play this game better
right next to size you can see she's
also got what direction she's pointing
in
and you can kind of like move her around
like this
which is kind of fun and after a while
you'll get dizzy now sprites have
different modes
you can see that right now her mode is
that she can point in any direction
i think she looks silly when she's like
walking up
and so what i do is i switch her mode
right now the mode is set to any
directions called all around you can
also switch it to where she's just left
right
or where she doesn't rotate at all i
want to switch her mode
to where she just does left right so i
fixed her size
so she's the right size and then i
switched her mode
to where she's just left right and so
now if she's pointing
anywhere to the left her sprite just
kind of looks like it's straight left
and if she's anywhere to the right she's
straight right so she's only got those
two options now it doesn't really matter
where you leave this arrow but i'm going
to put mine back to roughly 90 degrees
all right so avery is ready to go but
she has no code
the first thing we're going to do is
we're going to add a when green flag
clicked
so i'm still in my events area so i can
just bring it over
and what we want avery to do is we want
her for to
forever move and follow the mouse
so it's really mean to tell people to do
something forever but in code it happens
all the time
so let's see if we can find uh the
forever statement
so the forever statement is in the
control category
control is just below events so you can
just scroll down there if you want
or you can click on this word control
and what you're doing is you're trying
to find a forever loop
so the forever loop it's the third one
down right here so just drag a forever
loop
and pop it into place so now when the
green flag is clicked
avery is going to do something forever
and right now the thing she does forever
is is nothing there's no code in there
let's add some code in there
the code we're going to add is up in
motion so go on motion
um and find one that says point towards
mouse pointer
now this one's tricky because there's a
couple in here that are somewhere
but i want point towards mouse pointer
some people accidentally grab like go to
or something like that but point towards
will do it so if we're pointing towards
the mouse pointer
um when i run this program she should
point towards my mouse pointer now she
only points left or right
so when i run it and my mouse is over
here she points over here
and if my mouse goes on the other side
she switches direction
so she's pointing to the left she's
pointing towards the right
left right left right left right
you can also see that the code is
running in a couple of other ways first
it's outlined in yellow
so you can see that it's running because
it's outlined in yellow also the green
flag kind of appears that it's like
continually depressed
it's not sad it's just always pressed
all right
let's add some more code my campers
doing okay
everybody good all right let's do some
movement
so just below that point towards add a
move
10 steps
and the value 10 determines how fast she
walks
so right now i'm going to go ahead and
run it and she's going to move towards
my mouse at 10.
if you want to play with speeds um every
every kid likes to do this right so you
can you can go faster
but if she goes too fast it works out
badly right so everybody likes to do
that so i just showing it to you
you can go slower so if i go at two
she'll just go really slow
and i'm going to leave mine at 15 is
where i'm going to leave mine
that will appear to be kind of fast but
we're going to fix that in a minute
so you can play around with it but i'm
going to leave mine at 15 because i'm
going to do something
here in a minute that's gonna make that
be the correct speed right now it's a
little fast
another problem that i have is avery
is gliding places right i want her to be
walking places
now i'm going to show you something
about avery avery has code we can see
her code here because we're in the code
tab
avery also has costumes and avery has
sounds
what we the reason we picked avery is
because she has four costumes
and if you cycle between those costumes
it'll look like she's walking
so if you picked avery then you can make
her look like she's walking
so let's let's do that let's go into
looks
because her costume like the way she
looks is in looks
and find this one called next costume
and put it on the bottom
now i'm going to warn you she's going to
walk really fast
so you can see that she walks quite
quickly as she's going around
and it's kind of comical to watch her
but it is a little
too fast
so how do we slow her down um so the way
i want to slow her down
is i want to put in a short time delay
and so with a short time delay
it'll make her look like she's walking
not extremely fast
time delays are over in control so go to
control
take a wait one second
and put it down at the bottom of your
function the bottom of your favorite
loop so now
we're pointing towards the mouse pointer
we're moving 10
we're switching costumes so she looks
like walks um and then we're waiting
one second you can try one second but
it's going to be way too slow
that's quite painful and so i'm going to
switch it to
0.1 seconds
that i think looks good enough for me
so she's walking around and it looks
like things are going well
i think i'm going to come around i'm
going to check on some of my campers to
see how they're doing
and it'll give you a minute to get
caught up if you're falling behind
all right neela let's start with you so
have you got yours caught up
oh neil is a little on the independent
side neela
put a big old horse in there instead of
avery walking
um it looks really good can you show
that he moves around so you do
the green flag there and then as you
move the mouse around it's going great
bowen oh what a bunch of rule followers
bowen's got a penguin on here hit it
bowen let's see yours oh and the penguin
oh that's kind of neat bowen the penguin
has a walking animation great job you
two
five and seven you can do it let's check
on our our older campers
um so we've got mckinley uh with an
avery
yours is a little fast change it to 0.1
instead of zero one um and keegan's is
right there
mckinley says she knew what she was
supposed to do she just wanted it to be
fast
i suppose that's okay all right so the
next thing we want to do
is avery's looking good avery's walking
around a white
space let's go ahead and give her a
better background
so just like we added a sprite we're
going to add
a backdrop so in the lower right corner
here there's a circle that says choose
backdrop
go ahead and click on that circle in the
lower right corner
just like with sprites it will take you
to a screen that lets you pick the one
you want
what i chose to do is i chose to do
bedroom one
because i thought that it would be good
to be able to hide things in there
and to kind of make it look like it's
part of the environment i don't mind if
you do something different
you can do whatever you want to do but
just pick one that you think you'd like
while you're picking that i'm going to
talk about backdrops just a little bit
the first thing i want to say about
backdrops is that you can see right now
that my sprite is selected and i can see
her code
if i ever accidentally click on the
stage now it shows my stages code so do
this for me go back and forth click on
your sprite
and you can see your sprites code is
here and then if you click on your
backdrop which is over here to the right
you can see the backdrops code which is
blank i only point that out because
sometimes people
accidentally click over there and
they're like where'd all my code go
and it's because code can be different
for different sprites it can also be
different for the backdrop
and just know to bring your code back
all you have to do is click on avery
easy peasy all right let's add a new
sprite
so we want to add food for her to eat
alphabetically
and so this time i think it really would
be best if you follow along and you add
an apple
so click on choose sprite the circle
down here
and see if you can find an apple
now you can see that there's two
different sprites there's avery
and avery has code that we've written
and then there's an apple
which currently has no code at all and
you can go back and forth between them
pretty easily
the apple if you like its size you can
leave it i'm going to choose to make my
apple just a little bit smaller
maybe a 70 apple you can also put it
somewhere in your environment
maybe i'll do a 50 apple and put it on
the table to where it kind of looks like
it belongs so it's a little bit more
hidden
that's optional next let's write some
code for the apple
oh i just realized there's another
important thing that i forgot to do
uh whenever you're coding ask my campers
this what's an important thing to do
when you're coding campers
save it's important to save every so
often what i'm going to do is i'm going
to name my project
i'm going to name mine alphabet
breakfast
you can name your project anything you'd
like and it does
auto save but if you ever want to force
it to save you can click on file
save now so it will periodically auto
save so you don't have to keep hitting
file save now
but if you ever do something you're like
oh i want to make sure it's saved just
click on file save now
and you'll be sure that it saves back to
the apple
so the apple uh let's go ahead and do a
when green flag for for him as well so
click on events
when green flag clicked you'll find that
a lot of sprites start that way unless
you're doing something really advanced a
lot of them start this way
and what we're going to do with the
apple is we're going to decide to show
him or hide him so he's going to either
be shown or hidden
so the first thing i'm going to do is
i'm going to make sure he's shown
at when the program starts so go to
looks first
and find show now i know right now he's
shown and everything's fine
but periodically in this app he's going
to get hidden and i want to make sure he
starts off
being shown
now the next thing we want to do is we
want to forever check to see if avery's
touching the apple
so what i'm going to do next is i'm
going to add a forever loop
so i'm in control
and i drag a forever loop over
[Music]
all right now inside the forever loop we
want to check
if she's touching the apple uh this is
one of our our flow control statements
it's also uh in the control area
and it looks like this it's just an if
so drag this if over
and drop it inside the forever loop so
we're forever going to check
if something is happening now the way
you read this is it says
if and then this diamond shape is the
condition so if this condition is true
then run this code now let's find a good
condition to put in here
go into sensing so we want to sense
if we're touching avery or not
so this is kind of interesting but the
thing we want to drag into there
is actually if touching mouse pointer
and the reason we're going to drag this
in is you see this white arrow on here
so this white arrow means that you can
probably change it um
and sure enough you can change it to say
um if touching
avery walking so every walking is the
name of that other sprite
so um if touching avery walking
then we want to hide
hide is a command which is over and
looks
so we're going to bring in a hide and
drop it right there
so you can see that the apple has code
that it runs and avery has code that she
runs
and if i hit the green flag right now
avery's gonna walk around and as soon as
she touches the apple
it disappears it's gone
and then if you stop your program and
restart it the apple comes back
cool i'd say it's going pretty well
um another important thing with games is
that they're fun
right so right now the apple just just
disappears
i think it'd be more fun if our apple
made a little bit of noise
so our apple is gonna make a noise uh
whenever we get it we're gonna make a
chomp sound
all sprites have sounds that they
currently know about
let's click on the apple and let's see
what sounds it knows about sure enough
he has a sound called
chomp uh go ahead and play it it kind of
sounds like oh
on the apple so he already has the sound
we want if we wanted more sounds we
could add him but we don't need to for
him he's got the sound we want so let's
go back to our code
so in the code look for sound
[Music]
and what we want to do is we want to
play sound chomp
now there's a couple versions of this
there's play sound until done
and then there's start sound chomp in
this case it doesn't matter you can put
in either one that you'd want
um so let's go ahead and run it again
and now when we hit the apple
it should make a home chomp sound which
is kind of fun
i don't know if you can hear the chomp
on the video as well but mine worked
really nicely
all right the next thing we're going to
do is we're going to add a variable
so if you remember the main game what it
did is it had many
many different things you had to eat
right and we had to know
was it time to eat the apple or not
because we tried to eat the bananas
first
it would say keep trying food should be
alphabetically
but if you eat the apple first then it
should work right
and so what we need to do is we need to
keep track of the state of the game
the state of the game is a variable so
do this click on variables for me
and click on make a variable
i'm going to name this variable food
you can see that there's a couple
options here um it says for
all sprites or for this sprite only this
variable is for everybody in the whole
world
so the default of for all sprites was
correct
so i just need to type the word food and
then hit ok
now with variables you can see that it
shows it up here it says food zero
there's a couple things that we always
do with variables we always want to
set their initial value we want to
update them
at an appropriate time and then we want
to use them so
i want to set food to be one so i want
to set it to one when this program
starts up
i'm going to choose to put that code on
avery so click on avery
and so now we're back over in avery's
code
let's add some code to her what i want
to do is i want to add
set food to and so i'm going to drag
this
and i'm going to put it before the
forever loop
now just for fun that's where it goes
you should put it right there
i'm gonna i'm gonna pretend like i made
a mistake and show you how to fix a
mistake
so one thing that happens all the time
when you're coding
is you drop things in the wrong spot and
so let's say i drop this right here
oh no that's that's the wrong spot um so
the question is how do i fix it
the way you do it is you you drag it
over it brings everybody below it with
it
and then you drag the things that you
wanted back right so it's kind of a
two-step process
you'll get used to it with scratch so
where i want it is right here
and i want to set its initial value to
one
hey also while i'm over here let's go
ahead and make sure that avery starts in
the same spot each time in the game
so put avery to wherever you want her to
start at i'm going to have her start in
the bottom of her room here
and i want her to start there so that's
a motion command so click on motion
so i want the command go to x y
and i want to drop it in here at the
same time i set the variable
i'm going to set her initial position
your numbers don't have to be the same
as mine
and the nice thing about scratch is if
you've got her where you want her
those it's called the arguments will get
set correctly right so wherever
you put her in the right spot first then
you drag this command over
and things will work quite nicely so
start her somewhere weird
hit the green flag and you'll notice
that she'll go to your starting spot
each time so no matter where she's at
she'll go back to your starting spot all
right so this variable we made it we set
it to initial value
now let's see if we can change it at an
appropriate time click on your apple
so your apple um if he's touching avery
he needs to hide he needs to make a
chomp sound
by the way the order of those two
commands doesn't matter at all you can
have it swapped and that's fine
the other thing we want to do is we want
to
[Music]
increment the variable so let's just go
ahead and
quickly go to variables
and find change food by one
and drop it in here
[Music]
so let's go ahead and run it again and
this won't be that exciting but if you
notice food is currently one
but after i eat the apple food changes
to two
right so things are going pretty good
now the next thing we're going to do is
a little tricky so i want to only be
able to eat the apple
if food is currently one so here's what
i'm going to do
i'm going to take the code that i've got
in here
and i'm going to set it over to the side
so i still want that code but i'm just
going to set it over to the side
now what i want to do is i want to have
an if else statement
so we've we've learned about if
statements they were over in control
and this time what we want is we want
the more complex version it kind of
looks like a big letter e
and put in an if else statement
and so when we're touching avery we want
to check
is food equal to the correct number um
and in this case one
so if food is equal to one we want to
let you eat it
um if food is not one then we want to
show like an error message
so here's what we're gonna do we're
gonna go to operators
and we're gonna find the one that says
equals it's about six or seven down here
[Music]
and so if our variable food is equal to
the apples the first thing so if our
variable food is equal to one
then we're going to do stuff go into
variables
and drag food into that other white
circle
i did that kind of fast so if you need
to pause the video that's fine
but i went into operators and i grabbed
this equals
i changed the right hand side to b1 then
i went into variables and i grabbed food
and i put that on the left hand side
so if food is one then i want to do
this stuff that we were doing over here
so i'm going to drop this into the top
now what should we do if food is not one
does anybody want to say what we should
do if food is not one bowen do you have
any ideas
do you remember what uh what this
program did so if i tried to eat the
banana
what did it say yeah so if it's not the
right time we want to say a message
so let's go into looks
[Music]
um and grab this say hello for two
seconds
and then you should probably have an
adult type your message because it takes
forever to type
um so what i'm going to say is i'm going
to say keep trying
um oops sorry i'm going to say keep
trying
and then i'll say food should be eaten
alphabetically
now have an adult type that for you
because it takes a while to type
all right so let's go ahead and try it
now this time
we only have one food it's the apple
it's the correct time to eat the apple
so if you
if you hit the apple it should go chomp
um and it should be successful
we've never seen this message still
let's
make another sprite let's add some
bananas so to add another sprite this is
kind of a review
click on this green circle down here
and find the bananas for me it's still
pretty high in the order
by the way eventually we're going to go
to the food category and this will have
all the different foods we're going to
eat so i'm going to go with banana
if you want to do bread bread also
starts with b that'd be fine
if you want to eat a bowl i suppose you
could but i wouldn't recommend eating
bowls
i'm going to decide where the bananas
need to go into my figure i'm going to
make them a little sneaky
i'm going to say that these bananas are
sitting over here at the edge of the bed
now what we want to do is the bananas
need to have all the same code that the
apple had
the only thing that's different is
whether this food is equal to one or
food is equal to two
but it's mostly the exact same i do not
want to type it all
and sprite has a real or scratch has a
really good trick for this
go to the apple and drag the code from
the apple
um and drop it right here on the banana
it takes a little bit of getting used to
and you can see that whenever i did it
the banana kind of wiggled a little
and so if i drop it right there now it
it uh it's a copy paste is what happened
so now if i go to my apple i can see
that my apple has this code
and if i go to my banana the banana has
this code
i can tell that neel is struggling with
this drag and drop
mommy may have to help her some so both
of them have the same code
there's one thing that needs to be
different um and it's this
if food is equal to one the banana is
the second food
right so change it to a two
let's try it again so now
if i try to eat the banana first um
it'll say keep drying
food should be alphabetically
if i try to eat the apple first it'll
eat it
now i'm going to go eat the banana wow
so you can see it worked if we did the
banana
now we're going to mass produce some
food and my goal is for you to to do
this on your own
i'm going to help you kind of sort it
with one more and then i want you to
just kind of make a whole bunch
so to add the c i'm just going to do it
quickly here
i'm going to say choose a sprite i'm
going to click on food
and i'm going to pick a seafood i'm
going to pick cake
so now the cake is in here
and now i'm going to arrange the cake to
be a certain size
the cake then needs the same code
so i'm going to drag the code onto the
cake
and the cake is the third food so i
switch it to a three
so i want you to mass produce that um
for a couple different fruits maybe go
out to like
egg or if you want to you can go to
fortune cookie there's there's one
problem still with the sound
but we'll we'll fix that so i'm going to
pause the video
i'm going to let you add all the foods
that you want to add
and then we're going to fix the sounds
together after you add them
so pause the video and go add your foods
all right so our family had to take a
little break uh maybe you guys it's a
good time to take a break as well but
um i got mine added um so i've got apple
and it says food one check yours with me
so make sure your apple says food one
then click on your banana make sure it
says food too
your cake or whatever c you've got food
three
doughnut four egg
five fortune cookie six
now if you try it it will work right now
but the sounds may not work so when i
eat my apple
uh where'd my apple go to my apple's
right underneath my cake
when i eat my apple it made noise my
banana actually made noise
but then after that they quit making
noise um so why did that oh the donut
made noise
um so why do some make noise and others
don't make noise
i'm going to also move my cake a little
bit because my cake and my apple were
right on top of each other by the way
one trick for bringing them all back is
if you just hit
start and then stop immediately then
they all come back right so i like that
trick
since you can actually see things so why
didn't they make noise
so the apple you can see it says start
soundchomp
and then if you go to his tab he's got a
chomp sound so he's going to work fine
banana actually has the same code he
plays chomp
but you can see his sounds may not have
a chomp in it so what we want to do
is on the banana i want to switch it to
a sound that he does have so he has bite
on cake instead of chomp i want to
switch it to a sound he does have
i'm going to play birthday which is
actually a little long but that's okay
donut
instead of chomp i want i'll go with
bite
egg i think you see the pattern so
switch it to a sound he does have egg
has pop
that's fine and fortune cookie what's
fortune cookie guy he's got pop
oh well if you wanted to add more sounds
you could play around in the sound tab
but i quickly lose half an hour when i
let my kids go play in the sound tab
um so we're just going to fix like that
so now they should all make noise
so my campers are going to make a ton of
noise here so i get the apple
um banana birthday you're gonna hear
for like an hour
donut egg fortune cookie
cool so i think that worked pretty well
one advanced thing you can do by the way
on on the birthday cake its song was
kind of long
so you don't have to do this this is
optional i'm going to go into the
birthday cake and the sounds
and i'm going to click faster a few
times
and so it'll play a nice fast happy
birthday but it was taken too long
so i went into the sounds on cake and i
clicked faster
one or two times right all right
we're gonna add one more feature you
guys up for one more feature
one more feature when the game is over
nothing happens
and it would be kind of nice if
something happened
that said like congratulations or a
great job or you win
or something like that so we're going to
add one more piece of code
to avery so click on your avery sprite
her code should look like this
and we're going to add an if statement
in here so the if statements were over
in control
in the control area find if
and just like we did for all the foods
we're gonna see if that variable
is a certain number you can see that i
had six foods
so my variable ends at a seven so for
avery
i'm gonna say if food is equal to seven
then i'm going to play congratulations
you win things like that so i'm gonna go
to operators
i'm gonna find the equals operator
this is just like we did before i'm
gonna do variables
i'm gonna do food is equal to seven
all right so i've got that in there if
you ever need to pause it by the way
just pause the video and put that in
there
so when we win the game we wanna do a
couple things first i want to say
congratulations
so saying things is over in looks
and i this time i do care which i grab i
want to make sure to grab
say hello without any time delay on it
so i just want to say say hello
and you can put whatever congratulations
message you want again you might want to
have an adult type for you
so i'm going to say you win alphabet
breakfast
so type whatever message you'd like and
make sure it's the version that doesn't
have the delay on it
alright so i typed that for my camper
now we're ready to add a sound
now avery only has the sound of pop
that's not good enough i want a funner
sound
so make sure you've got avery selected
go to her sound area
and let's add a new sound so come down
here to the lower left corner
and say choose a sound
and the sound i want you to add is dance
celebration
so there's a couple ways to find dance
i chose to type in part of the word
dance because i knew that it was one of
the options
and i can see right here the second one
is dance celebration
so i'm going to click in the middle of
this white box
now that i've added the sound avery can
now play the sound in our code right
so i've added the sound here then i go
into the code
and on sounds this time i want play
sound
until done so i'm going to play this
and it defaulted to dance celebration
for me which was nice until done
and then the very last thing i'm going
to do is i'm going to end the program
so after i drag on play sound until done
i'm the last going to grab a stop all
so it's in control it's near the bottom
and it's a stop all now make sure that
this gets dropped into the correct spot
so it needs to go i'm inside this inner
loop
and that's our last line of code so it's
time to try it
um and then i'm gonna walk around i'm
gonna see how my campers did
so what should happen now is i should be
able to play my game
banana cake
donut egg and then whenever i get the
fortune cookie
i should do my dance celebration
all right so i think that mine is ready
to go uh but i'm more interested to see
how my campers did today uh nila do you
want to show us yours
yeah all right let's see it neela so
neela has a unicorn as we know
um and nila is walking around with the
unicorn
and she's got her sounds
and so she's got
cheesy puss for c donut
egg and fortune cookie
great job all right bowen let's see
yours let's see how bowen did bowens is
a penguin theme
so bowens has littler food so he's gonna
walk around and he's gonna eat his apple
great job and then his oh looks like
you've got bread down there bowen
and then a cake and then a donut
i forgot to make it
all right and then um your egg which is
way up in the sun
and then your fortune cookie
oh you made that one faster great job
bowen high five bud
all right keegan you're next in birth
order let's see uh
let's see yours so keegan is nine and
he's a big old stinker pot
so his are teeny tiny so you've got to
really zoom in to see his apple
uh it's in the poster so he's got an
apple
and then i have no idea where his bee is
oh it's a basketball
so he can see him with his infinitely
small vision
uh but i can't even see him
all right how many do you got left bud i
don't even know one more
oh and he's got a lot of foods he added
and then he's got a song there great job
bud
all right [ __ ] you're up next sissy's
our family artist
so of course she's got a craziness going
on she's got a butterfly
um and she's got flowers and she's got
food eaten
she hides after the song's over
great jobs this and then we're going to
get to her celebration
she's also got a fancy dance party all
right did you guys have fun building
your uh
building your program today yes all
right
i want to say one last thing before we
let you go uh so campers you can just
kind of
bear with me and listen if you want to
uh publish your project
you can click on the word share here and
it'll make a public page
that other people can look at you do
have to be signed in
to do that and then this url right here
you could send to a friend or family and
then they could see your project as well
so i think that's all i've got really i
just wanted to make sure that you
know a couple things you can sit on my
lap
first off is coding is fun uh you can
totally do it
neila is five this is her first coding
experience ever
and she's learning little bits at a time
right but we hopefully know that
different sprites
have different code the code runs in
order
and there's lots of great things we
learned today but we've got a whole week
of this
and each day will hopefully get easier
and easier for you
so we loved having you join us we hope
to see you again tomorrow
[Music]
bye